Register of the Roberto Cardenal Ch. Papers, 1957-1989
Hoover Institution Archives
Roberto Cardenal Ch. Papers,
1957-1989
88027
Cardenal Ch., Roberto (Cardenal Chamorro)
58 manuscript boxes (24.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photocopies of articles from La Prensa censored by the Nicaraguan Ministerio del Interior, photocopies of censorship orders by the Ministerio del Interior, the typescript of the book by Roberto Cardenal Ch. relating to the censorship, Lo que se quiso ocultar: ocho anos de censura sandinista (San Jose, Costa Rica, 1989), and correspondence, writings, notes, memoranda, and printed matter relating to Nicaraguan politics, censorship, and human rights conditions.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Censorship--Nicaragua; Nicaragua--History--1979-1990; Journalism--Nicaragua; Nicaragua; Freedom of the press--Nicaragua; Civil rights--Nicaragua; Prensa (Managua, Nicaragua); Nicaragua. Ministerio del Interior
Series Description
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1957-1988. (Boxes 1-6)
  Typescripts and printed articles, reports, pamphlets, clippings, serial issues, notes, agenda, and miscellany. Includes some background material relating to trips and conferences, a chronological series of La Prensa clippings (articles by Cardenal?), and drafts of his book entitled, El Verdadero Rostro del Sandinismo. Includes material relating to the Nicaraguan government, politics, foreign relations, the church, La Prensa, and civil rights, especially government censorship, and other subjects.
- LA PRENSA FILE, c. 1982-1986. (Boxes 6-24)
  Clippings and correspondence with the Nicaraguan government relating to censorship of La Prensa. Includes material relating to economics, education, foreign relations, human rights, labor, the military, politics, religion, social conditions in Nicaragua, and other subjects.
- NEWSPAPER SUBJECT FILE, 1971-1988. (Boxes 25-50)
  Clippings, primarily from the major pro-government Nicaraguan periodicals, Barricada and El Nuevo Diario. Includes material relating to most of the same topics described above.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1962-1988. (Boxes 51-56)
  Position statements and plans, reports, speeches and statements, clippings, outlines, membership lists, declarations, printed articles, serial issues, memoranda, correspondence, press releases, petitions, notes, and miscellany. Includes material relating to the Nicaraguan government, politics, opposition movements (both anti-Somoza and anti-Sandinista), and elections (Box 51), the censorship of La Prensa, freedom of the press, and human rights (Box 52), the church and religion (Box 53), economics, indigenous populations, peace negotiations, foreign relations, education, management training, and other subjects.
Container List
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1957-1988
  - General. Includes material relating to the Nicaraguan government, politics, foreign relations, the church, La Prensa, and civil rights, especially government censorship, and other subjects (Box 1-4.)
  - El Verdadero Rostro del Sandinismo, c. 1984-1988. Manuscript relating to government censorship of the Nicaraguan periodical, La Prensa
    - First draft (Box 5., Folder 1-2)
    - Second draft (Box 6., Folder 1)
- LA PRENS A FILE, c. 1982-1986
  - Correspondence with the Nicaraguan Interior Ministry relating to censored articles
    - 1982 March-August (Box 6., Folder 2-5)
    - 1982 August-1984 Feb. (most of 1983 is missing) (Box 7., Folder 1-8)
    - 1984 March-Oct. (Box 8., Folder 1-7)
    - 1984 Nov.-1985 Dec. (Box 9., Folder 1-6)
    - 1986 Jan.-March (Box 10., Folder 1-4)
  - Articles censored by the Nicaraguan government. Arranged by topic
    - General
      - General. Primarily relates to miscellaneous domestic events and problems; includes indices, advertisements and announcements, humorous articles, and reports from other Latin American periodicals (Folder 5-7)
      - General (Box 11., Folder 1-5)
      - General (Box 12., Folder 1-2)
      - 1983 (Folder 3)
      - 1984 (Folder 4)
      - 1985
        - Index (Box 13., Folder 1)
        - Feb.-July (Folder 2-6)
        - Aug.-Nov. (Box 14., Folder 1-4)
      - 1986
        - General (Folder 5)
        - Jan. (Folder 6)
        - Feb.-April (Box 15., Folder 1-3)
    - Bolanos, Enrique (Folder 4)
    - Corruption (Folder 5)
    - Economics
      - 1983 Jan.-Aug. (Folder 6-7)
      - 1983 Sept.-1986 May (Box 16., Folder 1-6)
    - Education (Box 17., Folder 1)
    - Foreign relations
      - General
        - General (Folder 2-3)
        - Socialist countries (Folder 4)
      - Costa Rica (Folder 5)
      - Cuba (Box 18., Folder 1)
      - Honduras (Folder 2)
      - Russia (Folder 3-4)
    - Health (Folder 5)
    - Human rights
      - 1982 Jan.-1983 Dec. (Folder 6-7)
      - 1984 Jan.-June (Folder 8)
      - 1984 July-Dec. (Box 19., Folder 1)
      - 1985 (Folder 2)
      - 1986 (Folder 3)
    - Labor
      - 1983 March-Dec. (Folder 4)
      - 1984 (Folder 5)
      - 1985 (Folder 6)
      - 1986 (Folder 7)
    - Military (Folder 8)
    - Military (Box 20., Folder 1-7)
    - Politics
      - General. Includes material relating to freedom of the press and the censorship of La Prensa (Folder 8)
      - General (Box 21., Folder 1-8)
      - General (Box 22., Folder 1-2)
      - 1982-1984 (Folder 3-6)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 23., Folder 1-2)
    - Red Cross (Folder 3)
    - Religion
      - 1982-1983 (Folder 4-5)
      - 1984-1986 (Box 24., Folder 1-3)
    - Social conditions (Folder 4-5)
    - Sports (Folder 6-7)
- NEWSPAPER SUBJECT FILE, 1971-1988.
  - Clippings, primarily from the major pro-government Nicaraguan periodicals, Barricada and El Nuevo Diario. Includes material relating to most of the same topics described above. (Box 25-50.)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1962-1988.
  - Position statements and plans, reports, speeches and statements, clippings, outlines, membership lists, declarations, printed articles, serial issues, memoranda, correspondence, press releases, petitions, notes, and miscellany. Includes material relating to the Nicaraguan government, politics, elections, and opposition movements (Box 51), the censorship of La Prensa, freedom of the press, and human rights (Box 52), the church and religion (Box 53), economics, indigenous populations, peace negotiations, foreign relations, education, management training, and other subjects. (Box 51-56.)